We were planning this
retreat, Tim and
I were thinking about what classes
to do and it's bad luck Buddhism not to
finish a
teaching.  The last Lam Rim took us 12
years to finish.
So let's give him a round of applause
[Music]
here.  And there's another important teaching
called Danen John Dep.
Dzen, which
means the tendency to think that the
pen or the ballpoint pen is coming
, right?  In other words, like being attached to
this pen that comes from a factory
and not from you.  Do you understand what I'm
trying to say?  When we believe this
pen is factory-made,
then that means you have this
mental illness
called [unclear - possibly "fake" or "fake"] and we all have it.  Even
when you're pointing at the pen, you're
having this problem.  That's
funny, isn't it?
But it is very old and it is in you.
That
tendency is like when you have a
battle, a fight with
someone.  So we have this, it's called
the
road fight.  Those who
drive around there crash into something like that.  The
two get angry, get out of the
car, like the rage of driving.
He says this happened to him and he got out of the
car and the other person showed him a gun
and said, "Ah, okay, okay, that's fine."
So, this type of encounter with
someone is called Shang in
Tibetan, which means like an encounter that
is a
fight.  In this book, which is a
long book of poetry, it is called The Fight Between
the Good Part of Your Mind and the Bad
Part of Your Mind.  And it's a
bitter fight, isn't it?  It's like those fights
you have on the
road.  My teacher told me about this
many years ago,
probably more than
40 years ago.  He taught it to us; it is very long,
and he could not finish this teaching.
He passed away before finishing this
teaching, and it's like bad luck not to
finish a teaching.  So I
thought I'd like to
teach it, I'd like to finish this
translation.  Then I'll feel
like I've finished it.  It's an
amazing book.  It's a fight in your
mind.  Your mind is splitting.
The good part, the bad part, you know?
The little devil and the little angel are fighting each other
.  It's an
incredible conversation, and it's a conversation that's
on our minds all the
time.  This person really
hurt me.  You say, "No, no, no. Do you
remember the
pen? Yes, yes, I know about the
pen, but this person is
different, isn't he? We all say this every
day. We all say it 100 times a
day. I do it every
day. I sit in my
house. I'm, my bottom is
freezing. What's the cruelest thing
that can be done to a lama?
It's the enoto. All the inoduos are
warm, they have electricity in the
seat. So I feel like I'm
in
paradise. Then I go back to Diamond
Mountain in my little house and I say, "Oh,
cold." I get up and say, "Oh, I don't know if
I can sit there, but I
feel like this."  Even at that moment I'm
arguing in my mind.  Inside my
mind there is an argument with my mind.  It's
a very beautiful book.  We started it in
What year, Tin?  Do you
remember?  We started it 14 years ago and we are still
working on this book.   I don't
have much time to teach it,
but I refuse to give up on teaching it.
So I'm going to be
stubborn about teaching it.  If you are a
person on the diamond path, perhaps
this book is for you right now.
Maybe you can
say, "Yes."
Maybe you can't say yes for sure, or you can't
say no for
sure either. It's possible that your Diamond Way
is with this book. Maybe this book
is supposed to help you on your
Diamond Way, and I take it this way. I
didn't finish this
book. It's going to take another three or four years,
probably, and I want to
finish it. It's never been translated
correctly.
I'd
like to be able to offer this to the world. I'd
like people to be able to use this
book. For me, when I teach it, I
understand it better. By explaining it, by
explaining something to someone, by
teaching it, I can understand it better.
You're going to learn as teachers.
When you want to teach
well, you can try teaching your
sister, you can try teaching
your children. How old is your son? 19.
Wow.
Okay. He's going to be a teacher to the one who
comes after him.
So, anyway
, I think the Buddha sent you this
book, and you're supposed to finish it
with me, so I'm making it part
of the Diamond Way course. It's
mainly a discussion about
about the meaning of emptiness, and it's a
unique book because it's funny, it's
hilarious, comical, it was written to be
comical, so I hope you
laugh. Sometimes just laugh, even if you do
n't understand it, just do it.
Ha, how funny, comical, and it's very, very
true. It's about criticizing
yourself. This is what half of
Grandpa's mind is thinking right before
I sit down in this special seat. Here
's who he blames for the weather.
Who made the weather so cold in
the morning?
Sometimes it's warm in the morning,
then it's cold later, it doesn't make
sense, does
it? You complain in your own
mind. That's the point. That's what's
called the
devil in your mind. Right now,
the devil is talking. And I worked
hard on this text
because you've heard about the idea of
mouths.
What's going on with
ACI? It's that
I think it's one of the
oldest organizations we have. I think it
started in '93 or something, but
like, '32  years
now. And it grew and grew and
grew and
sprang from there.
All the other organizations, SBDL,
BBB, they all came from here. And if
there's one, it's like 40 years old and it's gotten very
big, it's kind of big. So
if you take the 18
foundational courses, it's supposed to take you
six or seven
years, then you take the Diamond Way courses
and they should take you six
or seven years. In total, that's 14 years, and then
you have to do all the
meditations. That's another five years,
that's 19 years, and then you're supposed to
do a three-year retreat
someday. It
becomes like you don't have
time to
finish before you die. It's too much.
It grew so much that it's a lot. So what
we thought
was happening, that all of you
become teachers. We really
want all of you to become
teachers. So
foolish that they come and cook you in the desert
in these classes. You can probably
become a teacher,
because to be a teacher
feels similar to cooking you in Diamond
Mountain. You have to go through a lot of
problems, and we thought that the  People
who come specifically to the
Diamond Way are going to be great teachers. That
's my dream. That's been my
dream. That's what I've been
working on all these years. So
we think about so many things to learn, you
know? You can't study for 40 years and
then be a teacher because then you're
bald, right, John? You and
I. So our idea is
this: You can specialize. It's
like when you go to college.
You don't
try to get a degree
in science and another in English and another in
math. You don't try to do six of
these degrees in college unless
you're someone very, very special. So
our idea is that you can start
to
specialize. You're welcome to come
to all the classes. You don't have to stop
coming to the classes, but maybe you
can look into your heart.
And there are five options, basically there are
five majors, and you can have
your
master's degree or your graduation can be in
one of these five houses, and you can
teach, like the fraternities, like at
Princeton, you have to join one
of these houses, and you have  That you have to be loyal and
have support and friends and graduate
together at home in particular. So,
we wanted to do five
houses. The options are, what's the
first one? The first rule as a teacher is
when you can't remember something, you
ask the audience, "Do you
remember what's
first?" The
classics. You can go, you can take the
traditional way, you can
learn the 18 courses. Very good. Then you
can learn the other 18,
36. It's basically like a
getet course. If you pass the first 18
fundamental
ACI courses, you've covered the important things
of the
law course. By the way, they don't sit there
12 hours all day, they
constantly take breaks.
In fact, you never know if there's going to be a
class or
not. You go to class and then nobody's there, they
say, "No, no, we don't have class." They didn't
tell me. Well, we don't tell
people. They don't study like in
Western universities. The system
is a little crazier than it
is. I don't know. You're going to
finish this path  Philosophical. There are
people who like this as Word. There are
people who are like nerds and want to
study philosophy. I'm like that
. I enjoy philosophy and I like to
talk about it. That's how I learn.
If I ever reach old age, it's going to
be the path of the
philosopher. Then there are other people who
prefer
Samadhi, which is meditation. Some
people
feel...
they feel inspired by
meditation. It's like, "Here's another book,
the last 35 books weren't
enough on meditation. Read this one."
Oh, no, sorry, you tell them, "There are 35
books to study." And they say,
"Oh, I don't know, I don't want to read that many
books."  "What I want is to meditate."
There are people who prefer meditation,
and some people want to go deep into
meditation and
enjoy it. Their dream is to be a
meditation teacher, not a Tibetan master.
And that's
fine. And we should have a career
like that. We should have a house like that.
We should have the privilege and the
pleasure of joining a
meditation house. We call it the House of
Samadi, and you probably have to look like that
when you
graduate. Probably. By the way, great,
great, good
meditators are low-profile;
they don't show up. John Brady
is probably the best meditator
I
know, and he doesn't look like that.
His beard is a little
different—what I mean by
this is kind of
quiet. You don't look like that
. You can look like a
businesswoman. You can be someone who does
imports and
exports in a corporate world
in Vietnam, for example, and be a great,
great meditator, and nobody
knows it. It depends on
you. If you feel more drawn
to
meditation, when you look at your future,
You close your eyes and dream about the
future, you're teaching meditation to
a group of people, then you're
welcome to join this
house of Samar. It doesn't mean you can't
listen to the philosophy classes,
but it means you specialize.
When I decide what I do
, it's what I
say when I'm sitting on the
plane, when you sit with
someone and they say, "So what do you do
?" And if you're the person who's going to
say, "I'm a
meditation teacher, then your house should be
the house of Samaria." If you want to
say, "I want to be a guru," okay. They
say, "Okay."
You are in the house of the classics.
So, perhaps the third
house, we call them the
mountain house.  I feel very drawn to doing
retreats.  And there are some
people who have this hunger to
make a retreat.  Say, look, I have a new
book for you, I'm going to teach you a
new meditation.  They say, "Oh,
sorry, I'm busy."
Why is that?  I'm sitting in my
cabin.  I can't read a
book.  These people want to
be alone on a mountain
, in deep retreat, and they want
people to see them every 6 years or something like that, like a
manipal.  So, if you're the
kind of
person whose dream is to be one of these
greats, one of these great people
who take long periods of
time off, then you can join this
house, the
mountain cause.  I'm not sure what the
percentage of people is.  I don't know which of
the houses will be more popular, but I do
think that if you have five people in one
of the houses to start with, that's enough.   I don't
care.  I don't care if there are
100 people in the house of the classics
and two people in the house of the
surrendered.  I don't care about
that.  I want you to be where you want to
be.
The fourth
house is the house of the
stairs, it is Lamin's house.  Everyone's going to
call it Lamin's house.
In any
case, this has been a very important issue for the last 12 years
.  We covered an LR
in 12 years and I
have, uh, John's database has
like hundreds of LAMS.  You can spend
your whole life in the Lrims.  And there are many,
many beautiful books, the one we finished took
12 years, Rim Chen Mo
12. It would take 24 years just to make two of
these books.  If you can become a
teacher, that's very sweet and
maybe that's what you like.
Then suddenly everyone wants to be
in the fifth house, which is the
diamond house.  Diamond Way House
because everyone wants to be at
Diamond Way House.  We're not
going to allow you to be in the
Diamond Way house because then you'll
ignore the other four cases.
So we have a plan, Uncle Tim and I.
Our plan is for you to join one of the
four houses.   You do
n't have to say today, you don't have to
draw blood from your body and sign the
contract today.  No, just think about which one
appeals to you.  I'm going to tell you something
very master gave me advice on the
five themes of Gesche and said to me, "Is there
anything you really hate?"  And I said,
"Yes."
Which?  Course 13. Why do you think?
Why do you think that's an
unlucky number?  The 13th I hate logic.  He said,
"Perfect, you're going to be a master in that
course."  His advice was, "Go to the house you do
n't like, because that's the one you
're not so good at."  So when you
try to balance something, when you try
to be a master at something you
're not interested in, then you
become a master at both things.  You
're already a good meditator, perhaps.
So now learn how to do retreats or
learn philosophy or something like that.
This is also an option.   I
'm not
forcing you.  You always dreamed of sitting in
a
[Music]
cabin.  You are welcome to
join us at the retreat house, the
mountain house.  Whatever you like, you're
free to join it
.  But what we're asking you this
week, uh, we're going to ask you to
pretend that she's in one of the houses
to see how she
feels.  I told you my
wife's story, right?  That you will never, you will
never tell him, you will never repeat it to him,
right?  I took her to buy jeans in
Cottonwood, at this cowboy store,
where they don't have seats for
husbands to wait.  You have to stop there and
wait.  And she tried 42 pairs of
gin.  How many did
he buy?  None.
Zero.  What it means is try on
different houses, see how they feel,
how they fit you.  You are not
forced to take any of these.  Well,
yes, you know what?  No, it doesn't fit the
cone well.  What is the most special, most
amazing thing I did on a tour?  They are there and
he
knows it.  I was brave, I bought her a pair of
jeans and they fit her
well.  You write the story of my life
after I die, I should start
with him.  He bought his wife's jeans
and they fit him
well in Harry
Potter.  Kiri, how did you decide which
house to enter?  How did they
decide?  What's it called?
We couldn't get one of those
hats that, in Harry Potter, they tell you, you
put on a hat and the hat talks
and says, "Kiry, you should be in the
House of
Meditation." So we don't have that
hat. You're going to have to decide for
yourself. Where would Harry Potter go if he
could decide for himself?
Which house would be right for Harry
Potter? Like, he'd probably go to the house he did
n't
like. Anyway, the game this week
is that you're going to buy a gift card whenever
you say, and you have to say one of the
houses you might like to be in
. I mean, what would you
like to be a teacher of? What would you
primarily like to teach other people?
And you're going to focus on that, and we're going to
help you focus on whatever you
choose to do your PhD, your master's, your
postgraduate studies. We're going to help you focus
on that, and we're going to design
special courses for that. And it doesn't mean
other people can't come, but it's
primarily for this house. So we're
going to design special courses to
make you a great teacher of your
house, of that house that...  Choose. And then,
if you follow the requirements in
that house, you can also enter the
Diamond House. So, your
four-house path is a way to the fifth because everyone
wants to go to the fifth house and wants to
explore the four houses. All we
ask is that you enter one of
the four houses so that
you can then reach the
Diamond House. The Diamond House is like
the super house for people who
do very well in one of the four
houses, and then you will become a
master of these four
houses. So, the idea is that you
visualize yourself, see yourself as a
master of these houses. What is the most
important thing about the Diamond Path?
The teachings.
The
Diamond teachings talk about imagining yourself
mastering that teaching,
being a master. How does it change when
you are a master of that house, or how do you reach
your greatest potential? John Brady and I
would have incredible lion's manes,
and my stomach would be super flat.
So, this is one of the exercises
of the Diamond Path.  Visualize
yourself as you want to
be, and sometimes you can do that. We're going to
talk more
now about the fun we're going to
have. I call the book "The Angel and
the
Devil."
We're going to make a document for
that. You take the book like we did in the
last class. I have
Gson's book, "
Multiplier," and I open a space and
put an image there and teach from the
images, like I did in the
last class. I teach from the
images. So, for the angel debate
with the devil, I don't have images.
Why?
Because you have to create the
images, and each of the
houses is going to create images to teach
that part of the book in your own
way.
So today I'm going to teach you
some of the upcoming verses from "The
Angel and the Devil." And the thing is, the
devil really behaves like a... and he
really is a bad
person. He behaves with a very... disrespectful,
totally disrespectful attitude, which is what he
really does. And I would
like each of the
houses to guide you through this,
but I want you to...  They sit
together and design the edgings
, the images to
teach it. Then, we're going to have some
special classes. Each of the
houses is going to come and show. This is
the first image of the first
verse. This is like, this is the first
image of the first house, which is my
house, which is the best of the houses.
You have to be
super loyal to your house. We have a
Harry Potter expert here.
He read a lot of books in days, he
even read while walking. But don't do
that here because there are rattlesnakes here
.
I used to have an account and I would buy a lot of
pictures on this
account. I would search online, you'd say, "Oh,
I want a picture
of this," but then I have
artificial intelligence and it's
pretty stupid, but it's
getting a little better. And so
nowadays you can design your image,
you can ask it exactly. You can
write a sentence and say, "I want
a woman throwing spaghetti on
the Lord's head and he's meditating,"
and you write that and the
artificial intelligence does  "The image, and sometimes they
put five fingers on the
image." I really like it, and I use it
a lot. You'll probably
use video for AI in the future too, but in my
time, in my day, it's super cool. You're going to
use
AI, you're going to make an
image, and it's a great
teaching tool; it keeps the audience
entertained, right? So, you
show them this image, you keep them
entertained, and it's also really good to
ask your students later, "
What is this image about? What does
the image mean?" It should have some
power; it should be a powerful image
that tells a
story, and it's much easier to remember
things if you're seeing them in a
picture. So, we're going to tell a
story through
images. I didn't choose the images this
time because I want four images
for each of the main
lessons I'm going to give you. And I want to
see what each of
you, individually or in groups, can create. And
then Tim and I are going to decide which one is
the best, and you're going to get a
golden hat or something like that. No, that's
too
American. But anyway, let's go  Let's have some
fun. There was someone famous from
Mexico who has a new show.
We've been doing this for a long
time. We had, a lot of years ago,
we had an EDS contest. How
long ago? Like 10 years ago, something like
that. Actually, I was there, it was like 6 or 7 years ago. 7 years ago, and Juan won the prize because it was amazing. Juan was the one who won with that ID. He gave the explanation and everything, but anyway, he just got back from
Kyoto to teach and we should give him a
round of
applause. He and Adam
taught me and now it's me, Flavia,
saying, "Yes, I was there and I
remember that presentation."  Very
funny.  They did, Adam, and they
gave him a nice course in Kyoto.
Thanks to our
Japanese friends who sat there because
the course was pretty crazy, really crazy
, but Adamade and Juan gave some
beautiful classes and earned a scholarship
from Nick to be able to go and to be able to give
this
course.
The plane had to stop
in
Hawaii and Juan went to
Oahu and the
north coast.  I lived there for months and I grew up
there.  Which of these two beaches do you make
this face on?
Oajo or the north coast.
The
two are not
bikinis.  On the north coast, it's all about surfing.   It
makes you open your mouth.  Your
jaw drops, doesn't it?
Juan, I don't know which beach
you went to, but anyway, if you want to try
something like that, you can apply for one
of these scholarships.  You can talk to Tim,
to Nick.
And they went to Kyoto, had a great time
and helped many
people, taught a great course, did
very well, and everyone can do that.   It's
called GBX and I'll talk about it someday
.  Here we go.  I'm going to teach you about the angel and
the
devil, and as I teach, please
think about the image you're going to create with
artificial intelligence.   It
will help you in your
teaching career, it will
make you a better teacher, it
will help people
stay awake in your class and also
remember the lessons.  I
really want to motivate you.
My opinion is that everyone
in this class and everyone
online, you can learn to be a
teacher.  I believe it is everyone's
responsibility to teach this to other
people.  They are all different.
We are all
different.  Adam is not here.  So,
I can tell you something about
him.  His first
class was about 12 years ago.  He was in
Phoenix.  I coached him on what to say and he
prepared himself, stood up and stayed like that.
And I said to him,
"Adam,
Adam, Adam, sit down."  Then he sat down
and said, "Let's work on
that."  It froze.
I also froze during my first class.
My teacher told me, "Sit down and
be quiet."  Then you learn.  Okay.
You can learn.  You're going to learn.  In my
opinion, everyone
listening right now can
and should become a
teacher.
In the tradition of
old books, you are not allowed to take a
class if you do not intend to
teach it.  If you don't intend to
share it with someone, you're not
allowed to sit
here.  That's the tradition.  That's why
my cat listens to so many
lessons.  Sometimes nobody
wants to listen, and I say to the cat,
"Do you want to listen?"  He says, "Well, if
you have that kitty food that
I really like, I'll listen to your
chat."  Okay, here we go.
The devil is speaking.  Okay.  The
evil part of your mind says, "You should grab
people by the hand and lead them to
nowhere that exists at all."  Teach them
not to think about anything.  Make your
concentration filled with occupations
every
time or the meditation masters
within my
system.
Sit down.  Cross your legs and don't think
about
[Music]
anything.  Who is speaking?  I hope you know
who's talking.  Yes, the devil.
Okay.  And he says, "This is my meditation,
my system of
meditation."  You're laughing, you know?
But back
in the day, when I met my first
yoga teacher, I told him, "You know what? I do
n't know if I can do this
yoga thing."  It was
Ladyb, David, and Sharon.  I mean, oh, I don't
know if I can do this yoga thing
because I'm so busy, I travel a lot,
and they told me,
"Well, we have a suggestion. When
you get to the
hotel, look for a yoga class near
where you are and go to every country you go to
. Oh, I have a
wonderful story from Hong Kong about a
prenatal yoga class,
and the person in Chinese was saying to me,
'No.' And I was saying, 'No, but I have the
money, I have money.' And she was saying,
'Mine, mine.' Then I went in, and it was all
pregnant women.
It's the best stretch I've ever
had.
So, I want to tell you something, because
I've been to so many yoga classes in so
many countries, every country I've been to, I've
gone to a yoga class, and I never met
a teacher.
I heard hundreds of
horrible
meditation classes. Think about nothing, let your
thoughts go out the window. And
I was like,
'Okay.' Suddenly, by accident, I
realized. How much bad meditation
is taught? And I was kind of
shocked because I realized  It's
very uncommon for someone to be
teaching meditation.
Well, this has been happening for 400 years,
and this teacher, this great writer, Gon
Gson, he's the one who personally stopped
the war from his reptile cave.
He's saying that 400 years ago, he's
saying that 400 years ago there was a
problem with people teaching
meditation by saying, "Think of nothing,
try not to think of
anything." In this book, this is the
devil. And that's an important thing when
you form your
opinion. This isn't a bad
yoga class or anything like that. Ah. I mean,
often the asana class, the yoga class, is
good. Meditation is what's
ridiculous, but many times the
yoga teacher or the yoga instructor is
good; they teach good asana classes. That's why
I keep
going. On the plane, they give you
these earplugs. When
the meditation starts, I put the
earplugs in, and when the glossary starts,
I take the earplugs out.
You can go, you can
learn, but it's an
old problem of people thinking that
meditation  It's thinking about nothing.
Now,
listen, in a tantric sense, in a
Diamond Way sense, the goal of the Diamond Way is
that the work is accomplished before you
die. And you don't think about that. You say,
"Ah, Gel's health isn't so good."
Who's going to die first?  Who will
die next?  He doesn't
know.  Don't
think, don't think you know how it's going to
be.  It's usually out of order.   I
usually think I'm going to sit
here and not see anyone.  We don't know who will
leave first and we don't know who will
leave last.  And that's the way
things are.
In this system of the path
ahead, you are trying to reach the
goal before you die.  It's a
race.  There's always this thing behind
you, isn't there?  In other words, it's
haunting you, and maybe you'll die
tomorrow in a car accident.  Do you
remember that beautiful,
lovely lady?  Well, he died, he was in a
car accident and you're like, "Oh my
God."  It lasts 3 minutes.  Oh my God.
And then you're like, "Okay, what's for
dinner? We're all in a race on
the Diamond Way. See? I'm going to be
putting a little bit of the
Diamond Way in there, or kind of
passing it around in every verse. It's a race.
The purpose of the Diamond Way, the
reason for Diamond Way. One of the
important ideas of Diamond Way is that you
make it and then it fixes you.
Then if you don't die, you're okay, and if you do
die, you're okay. My death is
different from
yours. I know what's going to happen to me. I know
where I'm going to be. I know what's going to
happen five minutes after I die.
Everything is set up. The teachers are
ready for
me. Everything is set. Everything is
ready. You have to do that. You have to
take care of that while you can.
You have to take care of
that. That's the way of the
bad day. So this person who's
teaching you, meditating on nothing. They're
literally
killing you. It's not a joke. Oh, they don't know
how to meditate. They should have gone to
the
SMI house. It's not ten  Minutes wasted
before class. No, no, no, no. It's your
irreplaceable, priceless life.
I sold my company to Warren Buffett, and
I'm mad at him because he went from $
81 million to $143 billion a little bit
over what he bought from my company.
Now he's, what? 90, 94 years old.
Finally, his mind isn't
working so well anymore, but if he has
$143 billion, he should
be able to buy a couple of dollars
for somebody. He can't just go up to someone
and say, "Hey, I'll give you $100 million
a day, and you
give me a little bit of your time."
But you can't do that. They can't
give you that. Nobody can do that.
The person who teaches you bad
meditation is
killing you. They're stealing
priceless time. It's not a small thing; it's a
terrible thing. It's a tragedy. It's better
if you
got diarrhea, right?
R just had an
epic taste. I'm jealous because he lost  Like 4
kg. It
's not a joke, okay? It's not a
small thing, it's not like you wasted 10
minutes before yoga class, it's that
no one can give you back those 10
minutes, okay? Teaching meditation the
wrong way is like cutting off
someone's arm. I think it's
probably kinder to cut off
someone's arm because they can heal and
move on, but this is very serious, very
serious. It's a funny debate, but it's not
funny.
This character in the story
is really the devil because he's killing
people's hearts, not their
bodies, their hearts. He's
teaching them the wrong meditation. It's
a
terrible tragedy. Like someone dying in a
car accident. It's terrible. It's a
very sad thing that
someone would waste another
person's time. This is the devil bragging
about how fast his
system works.
You're going to find all the meditation that
they won't find. You're going to be able to enjoy my
system, or you can meditate for a month and
reach
opidad, and everyone is going to be free. Who
's talking?
The devil. Okay,  I'm listening. The
diamond path is the fastest path. I have
plenty of
time. If someone promises you
instant freedom, I want to tell you something like
an elder, some wisdom.
Someone
sits next to someone on a plane and
says, "Do you want to know the secret about
the stock market?" And I'm like,
"What?" Yeah, you have to invest in
a video. A
video. They have the chips, they have this and that
. It's amazing. You have to put
all your money in right now,
and then the founder of
Sony, the Sony corporation, right? What
's his name?
Mr.
Morita. That's what he
says. It's a great book. What's the name of
the
book? Made in
Japan. Great book. I love it. He
says, "Let me tell you something.  If someone
really knows which stock is going to go
up tomorrow, do you think they're going to
tell you?" And he says, "No, the logic was the
following.  The logic was undeniable.  If
someone knows
exactly that a stock is going to go up
tomorrow, why would they tell you?
They'd just put their money in there
and
double it. And he'd laugh and say, "I don't
play
with stocks." The founder of
Sony Corporation says, "I don't buy
stocks."
Why? Because it's like gambling. It's the same
as betting on horse races.
It's exactly the same. Nobody can
tell you where it's going to go tomorrow. You can
take all the experts in the world and they'll
all tell you something
different. And if they knew, they wouldn't be
experts, and if they were truly
experts, they'd make more money by keeping quiet. Don't
you see why I'm talking about this? Oh,
yes, because this guy is
promising you the
impossible. Look, I'm a
chant master. I have a magic hat,
I have the tin. I can say these
din prayers, you know? Look, look, look at
all this. Look at how I look, look at my
robe, look at my habits. That proves I
'm a
chant master. I have sex with all my
students, I take whatever
. I can  Get there in three
days. It's like this stock thing, you
know?
You say tin. Yeah, whatever. I'm going
to class. That's what you should answer him.
Okay. You
get me? The
hat doesn't carry your [ __ ] idea. I
have a hat. Do I ever
put on the hat? No.
Okay. Unreasonable promises that you
can reach enlightenment
instantly delay your
enlightenment.
Okay. To take on hard work,
steady work, you're going to have to sit on your
ass, in your retirement cottage, and you're going to
have a lot of tough days, right,
JB? A lot of
tough times, and then you reach the finish line.
The
diamond path isn't a piece of cake, but it
works. I like this next verse. It's
called a stupid guy who can't tie his
shoes. A stupid guy. Uh, Moran is
the English word, and it means super
stupid. Who's talking? Who
says that? The guy
from Y is accusing this beautiful angel
called
wisdom. The understanding of
emptiness. Miss emptiness. He says,  "You
're stupid, super stupid." And
she says, "Why do you say that?" She doesn't
get angry,
obviously. And he
says, "I'm capable of incredible
things, and you're just a pretty young
lady."  I have true
wisdom.  You're
super stupid." In English we say, "You can't
even fit into your shoes."   "
You're so stupid you can't even tie your
shoes." For Word Smith.
Never these
words. This is a
dialect in the
17th century. It means fool, dumbhead. What does it
mean? Basically,
he's accusing her of
being too nice. You're
someone who can't even tie your
shoes. You show up once and then
you're gone. He's accusing her of not
staying. He says to her, "Oh, you're so
beautiful, so wise, you understand the
pen, you
live by
teaching."  Why are you never home?
Where are you,
Tal?  Where are you all day?  Where do
you spend all day if you're not here?
Why did you never come home?
You are so beautiful, compassionate, so wise,
but you are never home.  Because?
What does he mean?
To really understand the
pen, you spend about two minutes with it once a month
.  Okay.  He is
accusing her of being a bad person, a
bad
wife.  The devil has to live with the
angel in a person's mind all
day long, and she is never at home.  The
devil lives in a
person's mind and she is never at
home.  She says, "Who is that
person?"  Ah,
he says to him, "Who is that person?
Where are you? Where do you spend all your
time? Why are you never here?"
You understand?
Means.  People think about
the pen once a week.
You spend all week complaining about other
people.  I can't believe this person
did this.  I can't believe this person
did this.  It hurt me
so much.  And once a month you say, "Ah, it's
because it comes from me.
That's what I do. That's what I
did. It basically means she's not
home very often. You understand? You're
supposed to say, "Oh, yes, yes, I
understand now." I think it's sweet. He,
the devil, is accusing her, the
angel, as if her husband is cheating on her
. I mean, who is the husband?
Ignorance. They live together, okay?
In our minds, it's just a
couple, and she's never home or not
home often. I feel like it's
sweet, it's funny,
comical. I want you to make a
cute picture about this, not a
weird picture, okay? Just a
cute picture about this, that she
's not home very often.
Okay. How many minutes do I have left?
About 5 more minutes.
Those who hope to accumulate in flesh,
of any measure, should come and
serve me at my feet. Who's
speaking? You could call him Mr. 2
Minutes. Buddha. Buddhahood 2  minutes. He
has the secret to reaching Buddhahood in
two minutes. I don't understand why
everyone isn't prostrating themselves at my feet. If
everyone meditated on nothing at
all, then I would reach Buddhahood in a
couple of days.
Okay. If you really want to be good
karma, merit, come serve the
devil. By the way, the devil in the
West tells you that you lie on your
taxes, for example, but in
tourism, the devil tells you to think
that the pen comes with a ward. That's
his only job. What can make you
believe that the person who insulted you yesterday
isn't coming from
you? So, he's done his
job. He's trying to make
you believe that someone else could
hurt you. And if he succeeds at that, then it
means you're his slave and you're going to
have a horrible life. You can keep
blaming other people your whole life. They
should be serving me,
right? They should be serving
me. You should be jealous of me
because I'm so powerful and you're so
weak. Who's
talking? The devil is.  Boasting. It's
true. It's not true that she's weak. It's
just that she doesn't come home that often.
When she does come home, she beats you
every time. If you think about where
the
pen comes from, then you would have patience with
people. But if you can't
remember, then you are weak. She
is stronger, but not if she's
not home.
If she's never visiting home, here's
your head, then she doesn't have the
ability or the possibility to show her
power. You have to
learn this old thing from a
student when you're sleeping in class,
what you have to do is this
manager. Yes,
that's the third level of
ability. The second level is you fall asleep
with your eyes open. The third is you
stay awake, don't move, don't tilt your
head. So you have three levels of
ability in
Shimaiko's classes. But now she says, "You must
be so tired of fighting me."
"Why don't you stop coming to the house?" The
devil says to him, "Oh, when you come to the
house you cause so many problems because you make us
wonder if this person is
coming from me or not.  Why don't you
stay?  So, why aren't you coming?  Stop
coming to my house.  Why don't you decide?
Why don't we just decide that
the person who hurts us is coming from
their own side and they are bad people?  And
then we don't have to keep
trying to remember the
hardline approach.  It's a
battle to be schizophrenic like that
.  What does schizophrenic mean in
this
context?  Oh, he hurt me, he said something mean to me
.  But it's coming from me.  Wait, it's
coming from me.  Okay.  No, it can't
come from me and hurt me.  So
how else would it be easier if you just
forgot about Buddhism altogether?  Someone
hurts you and you say, "Ah, what
jerks, what idiots, what bad
people. It's your mother's fault. Who
raised you that way? Wouldn't it be much
easier than this Buddhist argument in your
mind? Oh, maybe it's coming from me.
No, it can't be that you're coming from me. Oh,
well, maybe some people, but not
this person who is so bad is coming from
me. No, the devil says, "Oh, no."
Why don't you stop?  Why your wisdom,
Angel?  Why don't you leave the house and leave
us alone?
Now the beautiful woman
appears.  The beautiful woman wisdom
returns home and says, "Hey, honey,
I'm
home."  What does it mean?  You understand the
pen and use it in your life.  Some
people understand the pen but never
use it in their real life and continue to
complain about other
people.  And I'm complaining about
them now.
Now she is talking to him.
We have one minute.  Okay, stay
with me.  When I was sitting in
Key's course in a
refugee camp, 45
gros, raining down on my head from the ceiling and
everyone around me had tubers.
I made a
promise to the future.  Be a master, I'm
going to make them
yours. And now it's become a
reality.  I really did have that
thought, it's not a big thought,
but I had it.
An arrogant mind, you don't have a
single quality and yet you are
crazy and think you are a
meditation master because you can sit there and
think about
nothing.  Not only do you lack any
fine qualities, you don't even have the
tools to acquire
and develop those qualities.  In other words, in
this case it means, you don't even
know how to meditate.  No one ever
taught you meditation.  Do you think that thinking
about nothing is
meditation?  So you're never going to be
a good person.  You don't have the
tools, you don't have the
toolbox that is meditation.  You
think meditation means
sitting about nothing.
Yeah.